Guide to the Anna Grimshaw papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Anna Grimshaw Papers,
1939-2004
[Bulk Dates: 1983-1995].
Grimshaw, Anna
5 linear ft. (8 boxes; 5 document boxes, and 3 record storage cartons)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1553
8973986
These papers contain correspondence, manuscripts and drafts, interview transcripts, and printed material related to the autobiography / biography—which was never completed—of C.L.R. James, a writer, teacher and political activist from the West Indies, and to various C.L.R. James related projects which Anna Grimshaw, his one time assistant, undertook or on which she collaborated.
Biographical Note
Anna Grimshaw (b. 1956) was an assistant and editor for C.L.R. James--a West Indian writer, teacher and political activist--from 1983 until his death in 1989. Grimshaw, a native of Lancashire, grew up not far from Nelson, the town where James lived when he first arrived in England in 1932. She received her education at Cambridge University--a BA in 1977 and a PhD in Social Anthropology in 1984. Indian writer Farrukh Dhondy, a mutual friend of Grimshaw and James, introduced the pair early in 1983; Grimshaw was hired some months later to help James complete his autobiography, a project on which he had been working with a variety of assistants since the 1970s. The project was unfinished at James' death. Although the autobiography was never completed Grimshaw did help James edit his cricket writings and she provided friendship and aid in his last days. During the final few months of James' life Grimshaw moved into a house across the street from him.
Anna Grimshaw edited, wrote or contributed to a variety of C.L.R. James projects: she edited Cricket by C.L.R. James (Allison and Busby, 1986) and The C.L.R. James Reader (Blackwell, 1991); with Keith Hart she edited and introduced American Civilization (Blackwell, 1993); she also edited and introduced Special Delivery: The Letters of C.L.R. James to Constance Webb, 1939-1948 (Blackwell, 1996); she wrote the foreward for T he Nobbie Stories for Children and Adults, (University of Nebraska, 2006); and she edited and introduced a later version of Cricket--Majestic Inning: Writings on Cricket (Aurum Press, 2006).
The C.L.R. James Institute published several pamphlets written by Grimshaw or on which she collaborated including: "C.L.R. James and 'The Struggle for Happiness'" with Keith Hart; "Popular Democracy and the Creative Imagination: The Writings of C.L.R. James 1950-1963"; "C.L.R. James: A Revolutionary Vision for the 20th Century"; and "C.L.R. James in the 1980s: A Conversation with Anna Grimshaw", with Kent Worcester and Jim Murray.
Grimshaw also authored the exhibition catalogue C.L.R. James: Man of the People (London, 1986).
Currently Grimshaw is an Associate Professor in the Graduate Institute of Liberal Arts at Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia. Her research centers on visual anthropology, specifically ethnographic cinema.
Scope and Content
These papers include correspondence, manuscripts and drafts, interview transcripts, and printed material related to the autobiography / biography--which was never completed--of writer, teacher and political activist C.L.R. James, and to various C.L.R. James related projects on which Anna Grimshaw worked.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in two series:
Series I: C.L.R. James, 1939-1991
Series II: Anna Grimshaw Projects, 1983-2004
Subjects
Grimshaw, Anna.; James, C.L.R. (Cyril Lionel Robert), 1901-1989.; Webb, Constance.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Anna Grimshaw Gift 2009
Related Material at Columbia
C.L.R. James Papers Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Darcus Howe Papers Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Constance Webb Papers Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Series I: C.L.R. James, 1939-1991
  The bulk of this series comprises multiple drafts of chapters and sections of the C.L.R. James autobiography, unfinished at his death. The drafts are in a variety of formats—carbon copies, handwritten or typed—and for the most part are undated. Also here are transcripts of interviews of James, or of others regarding James; lectures or talks—most of which are transcripts—titled by topic or, if untitled, by location; a few writings; printed material including obituaries and tributes; and a sketch of James.
  - Autobiography/Biography
    - Chronology, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Outline, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Proposal--Biography, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Drafts
      - General, circa 1980s Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - General--By Section, circa 1980s Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - 1932-1938 circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Up to 1932 circa 1980s Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - 1932-1938 circa 1980s Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Black Jacobins, circa 1980s Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Coop, circa 1980s Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Early Days, circa 1980s Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Johnson-Forrest, circa 1980s Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Lahr, Charlie, circa 1980s Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Prep for England, circa 1980s Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Robeson, Paul, circa 1980s Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Shakespeare, circa 1980s Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Sharecroppers, Organizing, circa 1980s Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - United States, Observations, circa 1980s Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Williams, Eric, circa 1980s Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - World Revolution, circa 1980s Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Wright, Richard, circa 1980s Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Drafts and Notes--General, circa 1980s Undated (2 of 3 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 22 to 23)
    - Drafts and Notes--General, circa 1980s Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Drafts and Notes-- 1901-1960s circa 1980s Undated (11 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 2 to 12)
    - Drafts--Photocopies, circa 1980s Undated (1 of 8 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Drafts--Photocopies, circa 1980s Undated (7 of 8 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 1 to 7)
  - Interviews
    - by C.L.R. James--Leon Trotsky, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - of C.L.R. James
      - Interviewer: Paul Buhle, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Interviewer: Anna Grimshaw, circa 1980s (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Interviewer: Stuart Hall, Undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - Interviewer: Woody Haut, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Interviewer: Charles Nevin, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Interviewer: Al Richardson, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - Interviewer: Paul Robeson, Jr., 1985 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Interviewer: K. T. Sunitha, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - "An Audience with C.L.R. James"--Interviewer: Angus Calder, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - Cricket, Undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - "End of Empire--Interview with C.L.R. James", circa 1980s (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - "C.L.R. James and British Trotskyism; an Interview", 1987 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Padmore, George--Regarding-- Interviewer: Martin Page, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Pan African Conference-- Interviewer: Ahmed Gora Ebrahim, circa 1980s (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Pan African Conference, Focus on the Sixth, Undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Polish Solidarity, circa 1980s (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - "Shakespeare, C.L.R. James Talking About"-- Interviewer: Andy Erlam, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - "Talking History"-- Interviewer: E. P. Thompson, Undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - "Trotskyism and Black Nationalism: Some Political Reflections of C.L.R. James"-- Interviewer: Alan J. Pratt, Undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Regarding C.L.R. James
      - John Archer - Harry Wicks--Interviewer: Anna Grimshaw, 1984-1986 Undated, (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 11 to 12)
      - Robert Hill and J[im Murray], 1985 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Lectures and Talks
    - Address to Hackney Black Alliance, 1983 (Photocopy) (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Address to Oxford University Africa Society Day School on Africa--Draft, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - "The Best of C.L.R. James"--Reflections on the United States, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - "The Former Colonial World"--Cambridge University African Society, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - "Freedom Movements in the West Indies"--Radio Trinidad, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - "I'm a Poet," 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Johnson-Forrest Tendency Conference--circa early 1950s 1980s (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - George Lamming, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Nuclear War and Peace, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Shakespeare, circa 1980s (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Shakespeare in Brixton, circa 1980s (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - West Indies--General, 1972 1980s Undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Untitled--African American Teachers' Association, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Untitled--Rutgers University, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Untitled--Tougaloo College, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Writings
    - Art--James to Sura Levine, 1980 (Photocopy) (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - "Durham"--Incomplete, 1963 October (Carbon Copy) (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - "Perspectives and Proposals"--Facing Reality, 1966 (Typescript) (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Pamphlet--"Introduction to Party Politics in the West Indies", circa 1962 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Reviews, Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Personal
    - Clippings, 1986-1990 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Obituaries, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Printed Material, 1953-1991 Undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Printed Material-- Black Jacobins, 1986 Undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Sketch of James, Undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Tributes and Memorials 1989 Undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Series II: Anna Grimshaw Projects, 1983-2004
  Contained here are manuscripts and drafts, often with editorial comments and notes; correspondence; and research materials related to various C.L.R. James projects undertaken by Grimshaw including American Civilization, Cricket, and The Reader, and a 1986 exhibit C.L.R. James: Man of the People. Grimshaw also worked closely with Constance Webb, the second wife of C.L.R. James and the mother of his only child, on the selection and editing of The Letters of C.L.R. James to Constance Webb, 1939-1948, and The Nobbie Stories for Children and Adults—a selection of letters written by James to his young son, C.L.R. James, Jr., whom he had nicknamed "Nobbie". The bulk of the correspondence in this series is with other C.L.R. James scholars or with associates of James whom Grimshaw contacted in the course of her research.
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1984-1996 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Research Inquiries, 1984-1986 (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 2 to 3)
    - Buhle, Paul, 1985-1989 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Glover, Anna--C.L.R. James Portrait, 1988 1995 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Hart, Keith, 1987-1988 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Murray, Jim, 1983-1998 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Webb, Constance, 1985-1994 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Articles and Chapters
    - General (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - General--Notes and Materials, circa 1980s, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 10 to 11)
    - "Beyond the Boundary: C.L.R. James on the Arts and Social Revolution", Undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - "C.L.R. James and the Black Jacobins", circa 1986 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - "C.L.R. James: The Development of the Man and His Writing"-- Journal of the Cricket Society, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - "C.L.R. James, 1901-1989 A Personal Memoir", 1990 Undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - "C.L.R. James: A Revolutionary Vision for the 20th Century", 1991 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Popular Democracy and the Creative Imagination: C.L.R. James--Preface, circa 1991 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Articles by Others
    - General, Undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Buhle, Paul, Undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Farred, Grant, 1995 Undated (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Lai, Wooly Look--"C.L.R. James and Trinidad Nationalism", 1989 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - San Juan, E., Jr., 1995-1996 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Worchester, Kent, circa 1980s 1991 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - American Civilization
    - Correspondence, 1989-1991 Undated (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Introductions and Preface--Drafts, circa 1980s-1991 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Manuscript, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Manuscript-Early, circa 1950s (Photocopy) (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - "The Struggle for Happiness"--Proposal, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - "The Struggle for Happiness"--Preface, circa 1980s-1991 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - "The Struggle for Happiness"--Notes and Drafts, Undated (3 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 30 to 32)
  - Bibliographies, circa 1980s (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Cricket
    - Bibliography, circa 1980s (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence--Research Inquiries, 1984-1985 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Introduction, 1985-1986 (Annotated by C.L.R. James) (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Reviews, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Working Materials--1950s-1960s--Correspondence and James' Drafts--Photocopies and Transcriptions, Undated (2 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 6 to 7)
  - Exhibit: C.L.R. James--Man of the People
    - General, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Catalogue, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Chronology, 1985 Undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Exhibits, List of, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Expenses, 1985-1986 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Lectures, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - The C.L.R. James Archive--Bibliographies, circa 1980s-1991 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - The C.L.R. James Archive-- Surveys and Reports, circa 1980s-1991 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - The C.L.R. James Reader
    - Bibliography, circa 1980s-1992 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence, 1990-1992 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Editorial Material, Undated (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Notes and Drafts, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Manuscript, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Manuscript--Drafts and Transcriptions, circa 1990s (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Manuscripts--Transcriptions and Photocopies, circa 1990s (3 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 23 to 25)
    - Art and Culture--Transcripts and Photocopies, Undated (2 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 26 to 27)
    - "Literary Critics"--Photocopies, Undated (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Port of Spain Gazette--Transcripts, Undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Section 1953-1966--Transcripts and Photocopies, Undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Section 1958-1966-- Photocopies, Undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Working Material--Transcripts and Photocopies (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - C.L.R. James--Research Proposal, 1986 Undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - The Nobbie Stories for Children and Adults
    - Editorial Materials, 2004 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Introduction, circa 2004 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Manuscript, circa 2004 Undated (2 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 8 to 9)
  - Special Delivery: The Letters of C.L.R. James to Constance Webb, 1939-1948
    - Editorial Materials, 1995-2003 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Proposal to Publish, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Introduction--Drafts and Notes, circa 1980s (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - C.L.R. James to Constance Webb--Transcriptions and Photocopies, 1939-1948 (4 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 13 to 16)
    - Manuscript--Draft, circa 1980s (2 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 17 to 18)
    - Proposal--Drama, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Screen Play, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Personal--General Undated (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Personal--Visual Anthropology, 1991-1995 2001 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Working Materials--C.L.R. James--Photocopies
    - Correspondence, 1930s-1980s Undated ( 5 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 10 to 14)
    - Caribbean / West Indies, Undated (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Johnson-Forest Material, circa 1950s (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Pan-Africa, Undated (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Shakespeare and Homosexuality, Undated (Box 8, Folder 26)